Finding aid for the George H. Forsyth papers.
Bentley Historical Library
George H. Forsyth papers
1912-2015
1920-1999
Bentley Historical Library
Forsyth, George H.
2017040 Aa 2 UAl
18.25 linear feet (in 24 boxes)
68.2 MB
10 oversize folders
1 tubes
George H. Forsyth (1901-1991) was an eminent archeologist, architectural, and art historian who led archeological expeditions to Angers, France, Mount Sinai, Egypt, and countries in the Near East including Iraq, Syria, and Turkey. Forsyth was a professor at the University of Michigan, chairman of the History of Art Department and director of the Kelsey Museum. Ilene H. Forsyth, who continued George's publishing activities posthumously, was an art historian and professor at the University of Michigan. The collection is comprised of personal materials, teaching materials, and extensive documentation of George's personal travel and archeological expeditions to Europe and the Near East such as correspondence, field notes, and visual materials.
Restricted access in part. The following file is restricted until July 2022: Personal--Correspondence--Forsyth, Ilene, 1960.
Donated by Ilene H. Forsyth (donor no. 11704 ) in May 2017.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is arranged in five series: Personal Papers, University of Michigan Career, Church of Saint Martin Expeditions (Angers, France), Near East Travel Expeditions, and Michigan-Princeton-Alexandria Expeditions to Saint Catherine's Monastery (Mount Sinai, Egypt). The three series documenting George Forsyth's international archeological expeditions are ordered chronologically and are further arranged in subseries, described at the series level.
George Howard Forsyth was born September 2, 1901 in Chicago, Illinois to Sarah Brockunier and George H. Forsyth. He attended the Chicago Latin School, Lawrenceville School, and Princeton University graduating in 1923 with Bachelor of Arts and 1927 with a Master of Fine Arts. In the 1920s, Forsyth traveled widely in Europe and Near East corresponding with friend and noted art historian, Albert M. Friend. He documented his experience in personal writings, sketches, and photography. Forsyth returned to Princeton to finish his graduate degree and teach in the Department of Art and Archeology from 1927 to 1942. During his tenure at Princeton, Forsyth conducted a number of archeological expeditions to the Church of St. Martin in Angers, France, between 1926 and 1936, resulting in a published study in 1953.
Forsyth served three years in the United States Navy, 1942-1945, as a lieutenant during World War II. Following his service, Forsyth accepted a visiting professorship at the University of Michigan and became chair of the Art History Department in 1947, a position he held until 1961. Also during his time at UM, Forsyth served as director of the Kelsey Museum, 1961-1969, and professor of archeology, 1969-1972.
In 1954 and 1956, Forsyth led exploratory expeditions in search of a location to conduct a long-term archeological project. After exploring numerous churches, mosques, and other sites from antiquity in countries including Egypt, Greece, Iraq, Syria, and Turkey, Forsyth and his team settled on Saint Catherine's Monastery, in Egypt's Sinai Peninsula, built in the sixth century by Byzantine Emperor Justinian. The succeeding expeditions were led by George Forsyth in conjunction with Kurt Weitzmann of Princeton University in four campaigns: 1958, 1960, 1963, and 1965. Many scholars and experts were involved in the archeological field work and documentation of the monastery's religious icons and art. Experts included Fred Anderegg, University of Michigan photographer, Aziz Suryal Atiya of the University of Utah, Ernest Hawkins of the Byzantine Institute, among many others. Several publications resulted from the Michigan-Princeton-Alexandria expeditions, but at the time of his death, Forsyth had not published the landmark measured drawings he made based on precise field notes and detailed survey methods of the Monastery St. Catherine. Publication activities and a catalog of the drawings were compiled by Ilene Forsyth, George's wife, and Lois Drewer, of Princeton University, in multiple iterations in the 1990s.
Ilene Eleanor Haering was born August 21, 1928 in Centerline, Michigan. In 1950, Ilene received a degree in English literature from the University of Michigan and graduated from Columbia University with her Ph. D. in 1960. Dr. Forsyth joined the University of Michigan the following year as a lecturer and served on the faculty of the History of Art Department until her retirement in 1997. Dr. Forsyth held other appointments as a visiting professor at Harvard University (1980) and the University of California at Berkeley (1996). Ilene and George married in 1960 and lived in Ann Arbor, Michigan. George H. Forsyth died January 26, 1991.
The George H. Forsyth papers document Forsyth's career. The collection includes personal materials, biographical information, daybooks, family photographs, teaching and lecture notes, and extensive documentation of George's personal travel and archeological expeditions to Europe and the Near East. Material related to expeditions includes field notebooks, photographs, negatives, architectural drawings, correspondence, and manuscripts of various publication activities.
George Forsyth died prior to completing the publication of his landmark drawings of Saint Catherine's Monastery (Mount Sinai, Egypt). Publication efforts were continued posthumously by his wife, Dr. Ilene H. Forsyth, an art historian and professor at the University of Michigan. Her extensive efforts to publish George's work are documented is approximately three linear feet of manuscripts, correspondence, topical files, and a catalog of drawings, 1995-1997, located in Box 9.
Archaeological expeditions -- Egypt.; Architectural drawings (visual works); Architecture, Byzantine.; Architecture, Medieval.; Art, Byzantine.; Art, Medieval.; Art -- Study and teaching.; Digital file formats.; Europe -- Description and travel.; Excavations (Archaeology) -- France.; Field notes.; Glass plate negatives.; Greece -- Description and travel.; Icons, Byzantine.; Iraq -- Archaeological sites.; Middle East -- Antiquities.; Middle East -- Description and travel.; Monasteries.; Negatives.; Photographs.; Sinai (Egypt) -- Description and travel.; Slides.; Syria -- Antiquities.; Turkey -- Antiquities.; Anderegg, Fred, 1908-2001.; Collégiale Saint-Martin (Angers, France); Drewer, Lois, 1941-; Friend, Albert Mathias, Jr., 1894-1956.; Forsyth, George H.; Forsyth, Ilene H.; Kelsey Museum of Archaeology.; Princeton University.; Saint Catherine (Monastery: Mount Sinai); University of Michigan. Department of History of Art.; Weitzmann, Kurt, 1904-1993.
- Personal Papers, 1919-1991
  The Personal Papers series includes daybooks (1960-1991), correspondence, essays from George's undergraduate education at Princeton University, family photographs and negatives, and materials documenting his personal travel in Europe and Greece (1922-1925). Of particular note is the correspondence with art historian and friend, Albert M. Friend, a travel notebook and sketchbook, and 837 labeled photographs from Europe and Greece in the 1920s.
  - Books belonging to George Forsyth, 1929-1930 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    - 1950-1990 (Box 2)
    - Condolence letters, 1991; 2 folders (Box 1)
      (To Ilene Forsyth upon George Forsyth's death.)
    - Friend, Albert, 1924-1925; 1952 (Box 2)
    - Forsyth, Ilene, 1960 (Box Vault)
      [Restricted until July 01, 2022 ]
    - Lewis, Sue, 1969-1972 (Box 2)
  - Daybooks, 1960-1991; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Education
    (Primarily Princeton University.)
    - College entrance examination record, 1919 (Box 2)
    - Essays
      - Caesar and Cleopatra by George Bernard Shaw, 1921 (Box 2)
      - Renaissance Architecture, 1923 (Box 2)
    - References and bibliography, undated (Box 2)
  - Memorial exhibit materials, 1991; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Notebooks, 1950s (Box 2)
  - Obituary of Mrs. Henry H. Forsyth, 1922 (Box 1)
  - Proposal to excavate Marmoutier (France), 1934-1935 (Box 2)
  - Professional appointments file, 1927-1981 (Box 2)
  - Talks
    - "An American First: The Rise of the Skyscraper", 1981 (Box 1)
      (Scientific Club Meeting, Ann Arbor.)
    - "Modern Art and the Humanities", 1958 (Box 2)
      (University of Washington.)
    - "Problems of Interpretation", 1947 (Box 2)
      (Princeton Bicentennial.)
    - Skyscraper development, undated (Box 1)
  - Travel
    - Correspondence, 1922-1923 (Box 2)
      (Primarily from Europe to George's mother and father.)
    - Field notes Cheval Blanc (France), 1929-1933; 1 volume (Box 6)
    - Glass slides, 1925; 14 slide boxes (Box 20)
    - Glass slides continued, circa 1925; 43 envelopes (Box 21)
    - Notebook from Egypt and Greece, 1925 (Box 2)
      (Includes correspondence with Albert Friend.)
    - Notes, 1925 (Box 21)
      (Including Norman Towers.)
    - Passport, 1922-1925 (Box 2)
      (Includes detailed trip itinerary to Greece, 1925.)
    - Photographs buildings and various sights, circa 1925; 5 bundles (Box 21)
      (Identified and arranged alphabetically by Forsyth.)
    - Photographs from European travel, crica 1922-1925; 837 photographs (in 17 bundles) (Box 16)
      (Mostly buildings and archeological sites in Amsterdam, England, France, and Greece. All photographs identified by Forsyth. Numbering of photographs jumps from 632 to 663.)
    - Sketchbook, circa 1922; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Visual materials, Including photographs, negatives, and slides.
    - Art and archaeology session, Princeton Bicentennial, 1947 (Folder 1)
    - Beach, 1954; 1 envelopes (photographs), 7 negative strips (Box 15)
    - Family photographs, circa 1906-1945 (Box 2)
    - Hope at Camp (Burlington, Vermont), 1958; 1 negatives (in 1 canister) (Box 15)
    - Portraits in George Forsyth's studio, 1987; 1 slide boxes (28 color slides) (Box 15)
    - Unidentified negatives, 1954 (Box 15)
    - Unidentified negatives continued, undated; 7 rolls (in 1 box) (Box 22)
    - Unidentified woman and baby, undated; 1 framed photographs (in 1 box) (Box 22)
- University of Michigan Career, 1933-1976
  The University of Michigan Career series documents George's work as professor, chairman of the History of Art Department, and director of the Kelsey Museum. Materials include correspondence (1946-1973), a report on the 1956 trip to the Near East, histories of the History of Art Department and Kelsey Museum, and teaching materials such as notebooks on art history and lecture/course materials for various fine arts courses (1947-1957).
  - Annotated book reviews from The Art Bulletin, March 1953 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence
    - 1946-1973, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Gowans, Alan, 1971-1972; 2 folders (Box 4)
      (Includes printed material.)
  - Histories of Kelsey Museum and History of Art Department, 1967-1976 (Box 4)
  - Notes, article/book reviews, and lists of titles, 1953-1970 (Box 4)
  - Outline for "A evolution in congregational type church", undated (Box 4)
  - Report on the University of Michigan reconnaissance trip to the Near East, "The Medieval Islamic Period", 1956 (Box 4)
  - Symposium on Palestine in the Byzantine Period, 1952-1955 (Box 4)
    (Includes other general notes and printed materials.)
  - Teaching Materials
    (Includes notes, lectures, and other writings.)
    - "A Preface to the Study of Architectural History", undated (Box 4)
    - Bibliography and course syllabi, 1933-1949; undated (Box 4)
      (Includes annotated Princeton University materials.)
    - Fine Arts 3: Introduction to the History of Art, 1955-1956; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Fine Arts 45: Medieval Architecture, 1947-1959 (Box 1)
    - Fine Arts 166: European and American Architecture, 1955-1958; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Fine Arts 245: Investigation in Medieval Architecture, 1956-1957 (Box 4)
      (Includes notes on his philosophy of the writing of art history.)
    - General ancient architecture photographs and notes, circa 1930s; 1 card boxes (1 kodak photo box) (Box 22)
      (Card file organized by Forsyth, original order maintained.)
    - Notebooks
      - Ancient and medieval art, 1947; 1 volume (Box 6)
      - Introduction to art and English art, 1947; 1 volume (Box 6)
      - Renaissance and modern art, 1947; 1 volume (Box 6)
  - "Why an Architect" panel notes, 1959 (Box 4)
    (Freshman orientation session.)
- Church of Saint Martin Expeditions (Angers, France), 1912-2015; 1929-1951
  The Church of Saint Martin Expeditions (Angers, France) series documents the expeditions led by George Forsyth between 1926 and 1936 to Angers, France, to excavate the Church of Saint Martin, built in the ninth century by the son of Charlemagne. Forsyth led several expeditions to St. Martin resulting in the discovery of rare religious artifacts and important architectural data published in The Church of St. Martin at Angers: The architectural history of the site from the Roman Empire to the French Revolution. The excavations in collaboration with William A. Campbell.
  The series is arranged in four subseries: Correspondence, Field Work, Visual Materials, and Publication Activities. Materials include field notebooks detailing excavation activities, notes, drawings, and reference material; visual materials such as measured drawings, photographs of the church exterior and interior, and 162 envelopes of negatives of excavation activities; and annotated manuscript drafts, correspondence, and printed materials related to publication efforts. Files in each subseries are arranged alphabetically.
  - Correspondence
    - 1930-1936 (Box 3)
    - 1930-1937 (Box 3)
    - 1931-1940 (Box 3)
    - Aubert, Marcel, 1929-1936 (Box 3)
    - Campbell, 1930-1939 (Box 3)
    - Vendime, 1930-1938 (Box 3)
  - Field Work
    - Excavation of trenches, 1936 (Box 12)
      (Drawings and notes.)
    - Field Notebooks
      - Drawings
        - Volume I and II, 1929-1936 (Box 12)
        - Volume III and IV, 1929-1936 (Box 12)
      - Volume V, 1934-1940; 4 folders (notebook disbound) (Box 12)
      - Volume VI, VII, and VIII: Comparative material, 1929-1950; 4 volumes (Box 6)
      - Volume IX, 1930-1935; 1 volume (Box 6)
        (W.A. Campbell.)
      - Volume XI and XII: Descriptive and general, 1930-1931 (Box 12)
      - Source notes, circa 1930s; 2 folders (notebook disbound) (Box 12)
    - Notes and observations, 1930-1950 (Box 13)
      (Includes correspondence and sketches.)
    - Reference card file, circa 1926-1936; 8 folders (Box 13)
      (Includes photographs, history, setting, documentation, field notes, etc.)
    - Travel documents (France), 1924-1932 (Box 3)
  - Visual Materials
    - Drawings
      - Analytical attempts, 1934-1946 (Box 12)
      - Assorted drawings and reproductions, annotated, 1934; undated (Folder 2)
      - Chapter house, 1931-1936 (Box 12)
      - Ink plans for comparisons, 1950 (Box 12)
      - Measured details, 1935-1937 (Folder 3)
      - Restoration sketches, 1930 (Box 13)
      - Restoration sketches, 1934-1937 (Box 12)
      - Unlabeled drawing, undated (Folder 4)
    - Photographs and Negatives
      - Building exterior, excavation, and other unidentified images, circa 1920-1939; 2 folders (Box 12)
        (Many photographs have notes, most likely used in various publication iterations, others are unidentified.)
      - Loire school photographs, 1930-1931; undated (Box 3)
        (Includes notes.)
      - Old views, undated (Box 12)
      - Photographs, circa 1946-1950; 2 folders (Box 13)
      - Negatives, circa 1922-1936
        (Negatives are unidentified but primarily appear to be the excavation of St. Martin's Church. Envelopes towards the end of grouping appear to be of places in Greece, Egypt, and Turkey. Some images may be duplicates.)
        - Unidentified negatives, undated; 43 envelopes (1-43 of 162 Envelopes; nitrate negatives) (Box 17)
        - Unidentified negatives, undated; 72 envelopes (44-115 of 162 Envelopes; nitrate negatives) (Box 18)
        - Unidentified negatives, undated; 47 envelopes (116-162 of 162 Envelopes; nitrate negatives) (Box 19)
  - Publication Activities
    - Article for Antiquity, 1937 (Box 12)
    - Comparative materials, 1950-1951 (Box 12)
    - Correspondence
      - 1930-1951 (Box 12)
      - 1946-1952 (Box 12)
      - 1971-1973 (Box 3)
      - 1971-1990 (Box 3)
    - "Excavations in the church of St. Martin at Angers" lecture notes, 1947 (Box 12)
    - Manuscript draft, circa 1949; 3 folders (Box 13)
      (Handwritten.)
    - Notes, papers, photographs, 1930-1938; undated (Box 3)
      (Includes photographs, notes, a sketch, printed material, and other unidentified papers.)
    - Outline for publication, circa 1945 (Folder 5)
      (Outline drafted on oversize craft paper approximately 47 x 36 inches.)
    - Petit Appareil masonry, 1933-1938 (Box 13)
      (Includes notes and printed material.)
    - Posthumous request to Ilene, 2002-2015 (Box 11)
      (Including for exhibits, offprints, and biographical information.)
    - Printed materials, 1912-1931 (Box 12)
      (Annotated.)
    - "Roman, Merovingian, and Carolingian Constructions with in the Collegiate Church of St. Martin at Angers" paper, undated (Box 3)
    - Unidentified outline and notes, 1936-1947; undated (Box 12)
    - Volume XIV: Outline for publication (notebook), 1940-1945; 1 volume (Box 6)
    - Volume XIV: Outline for publication continued (notebook disbound), 1940-1945 (Box 12)
- Near East Travel Expeditions, 1926-1979; 1954-1957
  The Near East Travel Expeditions series is arranged in three subseries: Travel Preparations, Field Work, and Visual Materials. This series documents the two expeditions Forsyth led, in 1954 and 1956, in search of a site to conduct a long-term archeological campaign. Items of particular note include the field notebooks where Forsyth kept detailed notes of the sites he visited in Egypt, Greece, Italy, Iraq, Lebanon, Libya, Syria, and Turkey; correspondence, drawings, negatives, and the notebook (later exhibited at the Metropolitan Museum of Art) related to the excavation of Kariye Cammii (Istanbul, Turkey); Forsyth's equipment lists and trip itinerary; and photographs, negatives, and color slides of the churches, monasteries, and other sites of antiquity.
  - Travel Preparations
    - Anatolian studies notes, 1963-1969 (Box 2)
    - Bibliography for trip, 1956 (Box 2)
    - Clothing and equipment lists, 1954-1958 (Box 4)
    - Printed materials, 1936-1960 (Box 2)
      (Includes publications from the governments of Egypt and Iraq.)
    - Travel preparations, 1926; 1954-1956 (Box 4)
      (Includes travel documents and correspondence.)
    - Trip itinerary, 1954 (Box 2)
      (Includes letter from George Tchalenko and an eight page list of photograph identifications written in French.)
  - Field Work
    - Contribution to De artibus opuscula XL: essays in honor of Erwin Panofsky, 1958-1961 (Box 3)
      (Includes correspondence, photographs and drawings of the Church at Kanli Divane (Kanlıdivane) in Cilicia (Turkey).)
    - Correspondence, 1954 (Box 2)
      (Includes two2 letters from Albert Friend.)
    - Field Notebooks
      - All sites contact sheets, 1956; 2 volumes (Box 6)
      - Greece, 1957; 1 volume (Box 6)
      - General and bibliography, 1953-1959; 2 volumes (Box 6)
      - Near East and Africa, 1954-1956; 1 volume (Box 6)
        (Notebook indicates Turkey excluded.)
      - Turkey and Italy, 1954-1957; 1 volume (Box 6)
    - Kariye Cammii (Istanbul, Turkey)
      - Excavation notebook, 1957 (Box 2)
      - Drawings and negatives, 1957 (Box 2)
      - Ousterhout, Robert, correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
    - Report on excavations of Qasr al-Hayr al-Sharqi (Syria), circa 1969-1970 (Box 3)
  - Visual Materials
    The Visual Materials subseries is arranged by country, site or location, and alphabetically. The bulk of photographs, negatives, and color slides document sites in Turkey and Syria. Multi-site, or multi-country sites, include groupings of visual materials that could not be organized at the item level. Unless format is noted, all materials in this subseries are black and white photographs of various sizes. Please note that images were identified and grouped together based on Forsyth's labels; spelling of sites or locations may differ from current or originating language spellings.
    - Greece
      - Nea Anchialos, 1963 (Box 2)
      - Unidentified multiple sites, 1957 (Box 2)
    - Iraq
      - Multi-site, 1956 (Box 2)
        (Includes sites: Hatra, Mosul (Mar Isha'IA, Tahra of the Chaldeans, Shim 'un as Safa, Mar Yaqub, Qara Qosh-Mar Behnam), Qasr Sahrij, and Ukhaidir.)
    - Lebanon
      - Baalbeck (Box 2)
    - Libya
      - Multi-site, 1956 (Box 2)
        (Includes sites: Appollonia, Cyrene (Apollo Temple), Tocra, and Tolmeita (Synesius Church).)
    - Syria
      - Al Bara, 1954 (Box 3)
      - Baqirha, 1954 (Box 3)
      - Church of Saint Simeon, 1956; 4 color slides (Box 15)
      - Dar Qita, 1954 (Box 3)
      - Deir Siman, 1954 (Box 3)
      - Meez (Me'ez), 1954 (Box 3)
      - Multi-site, 1956 (Box 3)
        (Includes sites: Halibiye, Hawarin, Palmyra (Temple of Bel, Theatre), and Qasr el Hair.)
      - Qalat Siman, 1954 (Box 3)
      - Qalb Loze (Qalb Louzeh), 1954 (Box 3)
      - Quirqbize, 1954 (Box 3)
      - R'safah St. Sergius, 1954 (Box 3)
      - R'safah St. Sergius, 1956; negatives (Box 3)
        (Also includes Diyarbak and Qasr al Hayr.)
    - Turkey
      - Alahan Kilisse, 1954 (Box 3)
      - Altn Sehir, 1957 (Box 15)
      - Cambazli, 1954 (Box 3)
      - Dag Pazarli, 1954 (Box 3)
      - Diyarbakir Great Mosque, 1954 (Box 3)
      - Istanbul (St. John Studion), 1957 (Box 15)
      - Kanli Divane, 1954-1956 (Box 3)
      - Kariye Cami, 1957; 1 slide boxes (31 color slides) (Box 15)
        (Images of excavation work.)
      - Korykos, 1954 (Box 3)
      - Multi-site, 1956 (Box 3)
        (Includes sites: Dara, El Adhra, Hafsinas (Mar Shimun Zeiti), Hakh, Mar Gabriel, Mar Sovo, Zaz, and possibly other locations.)
      - Nusaybin Church of Mar Yaqub, 1954 (Box 3)
      - Qartemin, 1954-1956 (Box 3)
      - Sivrihisar, 1954 (Box 3)
    - Multi-country sites
      - Benson Murray photographs (Box 2)
        (Includes photographs and correspondence regarding identification of photos for multiple sites in Turkey, Syria, and possibly other areas.)
      - Contact prints, 1957; undated (Box 22)
      - List of prints made from negatives, 1956 (Box 2)
      - Near East and Africa Byzantine and Christian sites, circa 1950s; 23 bundles (1-23 of 31 bundles) (Box 23)
        (Card file organized by place/country, original order maintained.)
      - Near East and Africa Byzantine and Christian sites continued, circa 1950s; 8 bundles (24-31 of 31 bundles) (Box 15)
      - Rome (Italy) and unidentified locations, 1954 (Box 15)
      - Trip 1956, 57 envelopes (negatives) (Box 15)
        (Includes sites in: Turkey, Syria, Libya, and possibly other locations.)
      - Turkey and Syria, 1956; photographs (Box 3)
        (Includes Deir ez Zafaran and Resafe St. Serge.)
      - Turkey and Syria, circa 1954-1957; 7 slide boxes (color slides) (Box 15)
      - Unidentified, 1954 (Box 2)
    - Group photographs, 1954-1956; Includes 3 negatives (Box 3)
- Michigan-Princeton-Alexandria Expeditions to Saint Catherine's Monastery (Mount Sinai, Egypt), 1940-2012; 1954-1999